<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<knimeNode icon="./ocl_manipulation.png" type="Manipulator" xmlns="http://knime.org/node/v2.8">
    <name>Cluster Molecules (legacy)</name>

    <shortDescription>Clusters compounds using a simple, reproducible, but computationally demanding algorithm. Best used for datasets
        with maximum 10000 compounds.</shortDescription>

    <fullDescription>
        <intro>
            <p>Clustering is an old cheminformatics technique for subdividing a typically large compound collection into
                small groups of similar compounds. Clustering was used in the old days, when computational resources
                were expensive, to precompute similarity relationships between compounds. Cluster membership could be
                stored easily in databases to be quickly retrieved later, whenever the need arose to locate similar
                structures to any given structure, e.g. after a high-throughput screening. The inherent problem of
                clustering is that cluster borders are arbitrary and may separate very similar compounds into different
                clusters. Therefore, the retrieval of all cluster co-member of a given compound does not necessarily
                result in the most similar compounds.
            </p>
            <p>The implemented cluster algorithm is simple, reproducible, but computationally demanding and, therefore,
                best used if the
                dataset doesn't contain far beyond 10000 compounds. First the complete similarity matrix is calculated,
                which can be done with any descriptor. Then, in a stepwise process the most similar compounds or
                clusters are merged to form a new cluster, whose similarity to the remaining compounds and clusters is
                re-calculated as a weighted mean from its members. The merging process continues until a stop criterion
                is met. Stop criteria can be defined in the cluster dialog.
            </p>
            <p>
                The clustering process may be defined to stop when the cluster count reaches a desired number or when
                the similarity needed to join two clusters falls below a definable limit. If both criteria are defined,
                then the clustering stops if any of both criteria are met.
            </p>
        </intro>

        <option name="Input column">The column containing the molecules that should be clustered</option>
        <option name="Cluster column name">Name of the column that will contain the cluster number</option>
        <option name="Representative column name">Name of the column that will contain the information if a compound is
            the representative compound of the cluster
        </option>
        <option name="Stop clustering when number of clusters reaches">If selected, the clustering will stop if the
            specified number of clusters is reached
        </option>
        <option name="Stop clustering when highest similarity falls benlow">If selected, the clustering will stop if the
            the similarity needed to join two clusters falls below a defined threshold
        </option>
        <option name="Descriptor">The descriptor used for the similarity calculation. For more information about the
            different types of descriptors, please see the node description of the 'Calculate Similarity' node
        </option>


    </fullDescription>

    <ports>
        <inPort index="0" name="Input table">Input table containing the molecules to be clustered</inPort>
        <!-- possibly more input ports here-->
        <outPort index="0" name="Cluster table">Table with clustering information added.</outPort>
    </ports>

</knimeNode>
