<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<knimeNode icon="./ocl_manipulation.png" type="Source" xmlns="http://knime.org/node/v2.8">
    <name>Combinatorial Library</name>

    <shortDescription>
        Enumerates all products of a virtual reaction
    </shortDescription>

    <fullDescription>
        <intro>
            <p>This node generates all structures of a virtual combinatorial library if a generic reaction is drawn and
                for every generic reactant a list of real reactant structures is provided as an input. The enumerated
                product
                structures could be used to predict physico-chemical properties and to select those products with the
                most promising properties for synthesis or to be purchased.
            </p>
            <p>

            </p>
        </intro>
        <option name="Generic Reaction">Define the reaction that should be used to generate the virtual products. All
            atoms of the reaction should be mapped using the mapping tool in the editor. The reaction can be saved and
            loaded for later use
        </option>
        <option name="Generate ... of multiple possible products">Specifies if all or only on of multiple possible
            products are generated
        </option>
        <option name="Reactant 1">Column of input 1 that contains the molecules (Molecule) and the name (Name, optional) for the first reactant
        </option>
        <option name="Reactant 2">Column of input 2 that contains the molecules (Molecule) and the name (Name, optional) for the second reactant
        </option>
        <option name="Reactant 3">Column of input 3 that contains the molecules (Molecule) and the name (Name, optional) for the third reactant
        </option>

    </fullDescription>

    <ports>
        <inPort index="0" name="Reactant 1 Table">Data table containing the structures used as the first reactant of the
            reaction
        </inPort>
        <inPort index="1" name="Reactant 2 Table">Data table containing the structures used as the second reactant of
            the reaction
        </inPort>
        <inPort index="2" name="Reactant 3 Table">Data table containing the structures used as the third reactant of the
            reaction
        </inPort>
        <outPort index="0" name="Combinatorial Library Table">Data table containing the results of the virtual product
            enumeration of the specified reaction
        </outPort>
    </ports>

</knimeNode>
