<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<knimeNode icon="./ocl_manipulation.png" type="Manipulator" xmlns="http://knime.org/node/v2.8">
    <name>Scaffold Analysis</name>

    <shortDescription>
        Locates the core structure(s) of molecules.
    </shortDescription>

    <fullDescription>
        <intro>
            <p>
                The Scaffold Analysis locates the core structure(s) of every molecule within a given column and creates
                a new column that contains these scaffolds. The method used to locate the core structure(s) depends on
                the chosen Scaffold type:
            </p>
            <h3>Plain ring systems</h3>
            <p>This mode locates all single ring and annelated ring systems without any substituents.</p>
            <h3>Ring systems with substitution pattern</h3>
            <p>This mode works as the previous one, but marks every ring atom as being substituted, which carries an
                exeo-cyclic, non-hydrogen substituent in the original molecule.
            </p>
            <h3>Ring systems with carbon/hetero subst. pattern</h3>
            <p>This mode goes a step further by distinguishing, whether a substituent's first atom was a carbon atom
                or a hetero atom.
            </p>
            <h3>Ring system with atomic-no subst. pattern</h3>
            <p>This mode is even more specific. Every exocyclic substituent is represented by its first atom.</p>
            <h3>Murcko scaffold</h3>
            <p>he Murcko scaffold contains all plain ring systems of the given molecule plus all direct connections
                between them. Substituents, which don't contain ring systems are removed from rings and ring connecting
                chains.
            </p>
            <h3>Murcko skeleton</h3>
            <p>The Murcko skeleton is a generalized Murcko scaffold, which has all hetero atoms replaced by carbon
                atoms.
            </p>
            <h3>Most central ring system</h3>
            <p>As the name implies, this is that ring system of the molecule, which is closest to its topological
                center. It does not contain any exocyclic substitution information.
            </p>
        </intro>


        <option name="Input column">The column that contains the molecules that should be analyzed</option>
        <option name="Scaffold type">The scaffold used for the analysis (see above)</option>
    </fullDescription>

    <ports>
        <inPort index="0" name="Input table">Table containing the input compounds</inPort>

        <outPort index="0" name="Scaffold analysis">Data table containing the extracted scaffolds for each molecule in a separate column</outPort>
        <outPort index="1" name="Scaffold frequency">Data table containing all scaffolds and their frequency in the input table.</outPort>
    </ports>

</knimeNode>
